<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://martiluca.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://martiluca.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-05-30T13:53:45+00:00</updated><id>https://martiluca.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Writing a thesis in LaTeX</title><link href="https://martiluca.github.io/blog/2024/writing-a-thesis-with-latex/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Writing a thesis in LaTeX"/><published>2024-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://martiluca.github.io/blog/2024/writing-a-thesis-with-latex</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://martiluca.github.io/blog/2024/writing-a-thesis-with-latex/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="why-latex">Why LaTeX?</h2> <p>What is LaTeX, and why should you use it to write your thesis? LaTeX is a typesetting system widely used in academia, particularly for technical and scientific documents, which offers a series of advantages over traditional word processors:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Superior Typesetting Quality and Consistent Formatting.</strong> One of LaTeX’s best qualities is its consistency, which ensures that your thesis not only reads well but also looks professional.</li> <li><strong>Great Handling of Mathematical Content.</strong> Thesis in STEM fields often involve an extensive use of mathematical formulas and equations. LaTeX provides a powerful equation editor that allows you to write and format complex equations with ease; moreover, referencing them is easy, thanks to the labeling system.</li> <li><strong>Efficient Citation Management.</strong> Thanks to tools like BibTeX and BibLaTeX, managing references and citations is fast and efficient.</li> <li><strong>Flexibility and Customization.</strong> LaTeX offers many customization options. You can tailor the appearance of your thesis to meet specific guidelines or personal preferences. You can change the look of a whole document in a matter of seconds, and it will keep its consistency.</li> <li><strong>Learning and Community Support.</strong> Although LaTeX has a steeper learning curve than traditional word processors, the investment in learning it pays off. Moreover, a vast community of LaTeX users and a wealth of resources are available, including tutorials, templates, and forums where you can seek and share advice.</li> </ol> <h2 id="ok-but-where-do-i-start">Ok, but where do I start?</h2> <p>With that said, where should you start when trying to learn LaTeX? In my opinion, the easiest way is to use an online editor like <a href="https://it.overleaf.com/">Overleaf</a>, which does not require you to install anything and allows for real-time collaboration for free. This has its limitations (it’s slow at compiling, and the free plan also has a compilation time limit), but it’s a great starting point. Pair this with the hundreds of templates already available on this and other websites, and you will be writing documents in no time.</p> <p>In this article, I will explain how to use my particular template, which can be found here, but you can try to follow along with similar templates. One I highly suggest taking a look at once you grasp LaTeX basics is <a href="https://it.overleaf.com/latex/templates/classic-thesis-style-v4-dot-2-by-andre-miede/dwgtvykzvdtk">Classic Thesis</a> by André Miede.</p> <h3 id="the-title-page">The Title Page</h3> <p>Once you downloaded the zip and opened it with your preferred editor (on Overleaf, you can start a new project by simply uploading the zip file), you will see the following file structure:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>.
├── backmatter/
│   └── acknowledgements.tex
├── chapters/
│   └── introduction.tex
├── figures
├── frontmatter/
│   ├── abstract.tex
│   ├── dedication.tex
│   ├── logo.png
│   └── titlepage.tex
├── settings/
│   ├── fonts
│   └── commands.tex
├── main.tex
├── ref.bib
└── SciThesis.cls
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Once you understand how this structure works, you can easily add and remove things. First, let’s change the Title Page! Open the relative file <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">titlepage.tex</code>: here, you can insert your university name, department, course, title, supervisors’ name, academic year, and your name and matriculation number.</p> <blockquote class="block-warning"> <h5 id="warning">WARNING</h5> <p>This template uses custom fonts! You will have to change the compiler from pdfLaTeX to either XeLaTeX or LuaLaTeX!</p> <p>To do so in overleaf, click the Menu button in the top left corner. You will find the compiler option in the Settings section.</p> </blockquote> <h3 id="managing-and-adding-chapters">Managing and adding chapters</h3> <p>As you can see, I added a dedication page. You can choose to remove it by removing or commenting the following lines in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main.tex</code> file:</p> <div class="language-latex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c">% Dedication</span>
<span class="k">\include</span><span class="p">{</span>frontmatter/dedication<span class="p">}</span>
    
<span class="c">% insert blank page</span>
<span class="k">\newpage</span>
<span class="k">\thispagestyle</span><span class="p">{</span>empty<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="k">\mbox</span><span class="p">{}</span>
<span class="k">\newpage</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>To modify other sections, like the abstract or the introduction, you can go to their respective files: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">./frontmatter/abstract.tex</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">./chapters/introduction.tex</code>. If you want to add other section, do so by creating the relative tex file in the appropriate folder; the add it to the main document by including it in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main.tex</code> file: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">\include{path/to/document.tex}</code>.</p> <blockquote class="block-tip"> <h5 id="tip">TIP</h5> <p>If you are having trouble with anything, I suggest you refer to the Overleaf tutorials. Usually, you can find everything you may need there. Moreover, I suggest the <a href="https://github.com/PacktPublishing/LaTeX-Cookbook">LaTeX Cookbook</a> by Stefan Kottwitz, a book that teaches you how to solve common problems when using LaTeX.</p> </blockquote> <h3 id="customization">Customization</h3> <p>You can customize how things look in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SciThesis.cls</code>file. Here, you can manage packages and other layout preferences.</p> <p>You can customize how theorems, code portions, labels, and other things look.</p> <p>The easiest thing you can customize is the main color for the Chapters and links:</p> <div class="language-latex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>40 <span class="k">\definecolor</span><span class="p">{</span>maincolor<span class="p">}{</span>RGB<span class="p">}{</span>51,127,128<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Here, you can change the RGB definition to any color you want. The default one is teal.</p> <h2 id="whats-next">What’s next?</h2> <p>This is just an introductory post to get this template up and running. In the next weeks, I will write more specific tutorials on how to handle common situations you may encounter when writing your thesis, starting with bibliography management.</p> <p>See you next time!</p>]]></content><author><name>Martina Lucà</name></author><category term="LaTeX"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="thesis"/><category term="latex"/><category term="template"/><category term="stem"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Why you should write your thesis in LaTeX? Start here and give it a try!]]></summary></entry></feed>