<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://martiluca.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://martiluca.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-06-08T12:42:17+00:00</updated><id>https://martiluca.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Managing your bibliography with Zotero and BibLaTeX</title><link href="https://martiluca.github.io/blog/2024/managing-your-bibliography-with-zotero-and-bibilatex/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Managing your bibliography with Zotero and BibLaTeX"/><published>2024-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://martiluca.github.io/blog/2024/managing-your-bibliography-with-zotero-and-bibilatex</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://martiluca.github.io/blog/2024/managing-your-bibliography-with-zotero-and-bibilatex/"><![CDATA[<p>When writing your thesis, managing references and bibliographies can often become a daunting task. Mismanaging your references can lead to inconsistencies, errors, and a significant amount of wasted time. This is when Zotero comes in handy. First of all, what is it? It’s an open-source reference management tool designed to help you collect, organize, cite, and share your research sources. Pair this with BibLaTeX, a package that provides advanced bibliographic features and formatting capabilities, and you have the power to manage and format your bibliographies with precision, ease, and consistency.</p> <h2 id="prepare-zotero">Prepare Zotero</h2> <p>You can download Zotero <a href="https://www.zotero.org/">here</a>. I suggest pairing it with the appropriate Zotero connector extension for your browser (you can find it <a href="https://www.zotero.org/download/connectors">here</a>) to make it really easy to add articles, books, and web pages to your collections.</p> <p>Since we are looking to pair it with Biber, we will need to install a plug-in called Better BibTeX. To do so head over <a href="https://github.com/retorquere/zotero-better-bibtex/releases">here</a> and download the most recent release. To install it head back to Zotero and perform the following steps:</p> <ol> <li>In the main menu go to Tools &gt; Add-ons</li> <li>Select ‘Extensions’</li> <li>Click on the gear in the top-right corner and choose ‘Install Add-on From File…’</li> <li>Choose .xpi that you’ve just downloaded, and click ‘Install’</li> <li>Restart Zotero if you’re using Zotero 6</li> </ol> <p>After the initial installation, the plugin will auto-update to newer releases.</p> <h2 id="exporting-zotero-to-bibtex">Exporting Zotero to BibTeX</h2> <p>Start by launching Zotero and select the references you wish to export. This can include all references in a particular folder or specific ones highlighted using control-clicks and shift-clicks.</p> <p>Go to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">File</code> and choose <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Export Library</code>. In the dialog box that appears, select the better BibTeX format and click OK. If you are working locally, you can save this file directly in the directory of your project and select the option <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Export Notes</code>. If you wish to update your .bib file every time you add a reference to your collection, select also the option <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Keep updated</code>.</p> <h3 id="using-zotero-with-overleaf">Using Zotero with Overleaf</h3> <p>Last time, I suggested using Overleaf if you are a beginner. If you have a premium license, Overleaf offers a direct integration with Zotero. To link your Overleaf account to Zotero, you can follow Overealf’s tutorial, which can be found <a href="https://it.overleaf.com/learn/how-to/How_to_link_your_Overleaf_account_to_Mendeley_and_Zotero">here</a>.</p> <p>If you do not own a premium license, do not worry! You can simply follow the process described above and just upload the resulting .bib file to your project. To keep it updated, you can just copy and paste the content of your local copy to the one on Overleaf.</p> <p>In my <a href="https://github.com/martiluca/SciThesis">Thesis template</a>, you already have a ref.bib file in which you can copy and paste the content of your Zotero-generated .bib file as you add references to your collection.</p> <p>Your .bib file will look something like this:</p> <div class="language-latex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>@book<span class="p">{</span>smith2020example,
  author    = <span class="p">{</span>John Smith<span class="p">}</span>,
  title     = <span class="p">{</span>An Example Book<span class="p">}</span>,
  year      = <span class="p">{</span>2020<span class="p">}</span>,
  publisher = <span class="p">{</span>Example Publisher<span class="p">}</span>,
  address   = <span class="p">{</span>Example City<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

@article<span class="p">{</span>johnson2019example,
  author    = <span class="p">{</span>Emily Johnson and Michael Doe<span class="p">}</span>,
  title     = <span class="p">{</span>An Example Article<span class="p">}</span>,
  journal   = <span class="p">{</span>Journal of Examples<span class="p">}</span>,
  year      = <span class="p">{</span>2019<span class="p">}</span>,
  volume    = <span class="p">{</span>10<span class="p">}</span>,
  number    = <span class="p">{</span>2<span class="p">}</span>,
  pages     = <span class="p">{</span>123-145<span class="p">}</span>,
  month     = <span class="p">{</span>March<span class="p">}</span>,
  doi       = <span class="p">{</span>10.1234/example.doi<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

@inproceedings<span class="p">{</span>doe2018example,
  author    = <span class="p">{</span>Jane Doe<span class="p">}</span>,
  title     = <span class="p">{</span>An Example Conference Paper<span class="p">}</span>,
  booktitle = <span class="p">{</span>Proceedings of the Example Conference<span class="p">}</span>,
  year      = <span class="p">{</span>2018<span class="p">}</span>,
  editor    = <span class="p">{</span>Ann Editor<span class="p">}</span>,
  volume    = <span class="p">{</span>1<span class="p">}</span>,
  series    = <span class="p">{</span>Example Series<span class="p">}</span>,
  pages     = <span class="p">{</span>50-60<span class="p">}</span>,
  address   = <span class="p">{</span>Example Location<span class="p">}</span>,
  month     = <span class="p">{</span>July<span class="p">}</span>,
  organization = <span class="p">{</span>Example Organization<span class="p">}</span>,
  publisher = <span class="p">{</span>Example Publisher<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

@misc<span class="p">{</span>unknown2021example,
  author       = <span class="p">{</span>Anonymous<span class="p">}</span>,
  title        = <span class="p">{</span>An Example Webpage<span class="p">}</span>,
  year         = <span class="p">{</span>2021<span class="p">}</span>,
  howpublished = <span class="p">{</span><span class="k">\url</span><span class="p">{</span>https://www.example.com<span class="p">}}</span>,
  note         = <span class="p">{</span>Accessed: 2024-06-03<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <h2 id="using-the-references-in-your-document">Using the references in your document</h2> <p>Now that you have built a collection and exported a .bib file, it’s time to cite your sources in your LaTeX document.</p> <p>To cite a source, use the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">\cite{}</code> command, where the argument is the citation key for the reference you want to cite. The citation key is typically generated automatically by Zotero and can be found in the .bib file right after the @entry_type.</p> <p>Here is an example of how to cite a source within your document:</p> <div class="language-latex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>As shown in previous studies <span class="k">\cite</span><span class="p">{</span>smith2020example<span class="p">}</span>, the results indicate significant improvements.
</code></pre></div></div> <p>This command will insert a reference in the text and add the corresponding citation in the bibliography section.</p> <p><strong>Inline citations</strong></p> <p>If you need to include the author’s name as part of the narrative, you can use the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">\textcite{}</code> command provided by BibLaTeX:</p> <div class="language-latex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Smith et al. <span class="k">\textcite</span><span class="p">{</span>smith2020example<span class="p">}</span> demonstrated significant improvements in their study.
</code></pre></div></div> <p><strong>Multiple citations</strong></p> <p>To cite multiple references at once, include all the citation keys separated by commas within the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">\cite{}</code> command:</p> <div class="language-latex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Several studies have explored this phenomenon <span class="k">\cite</span><span class="p">{</span>smith2020example, johnson2019example, doe2018example<span class="p">}</span>.
</code></pre></div></div> <p>If you are using the settings found in my template, your citations and bibliography will look like this:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/citations-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/citations-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/citations-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/citations.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/bib-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/bib-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/bib-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/bib.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="customize-the-look-of-your-citations-and-bibliography">Customize the look of your citations and bibliography</h2> <p>You can find the bibliography settings at the bottom of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SciThesis.cls</code> file:</p> <div class="language-latex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c">%% BIBLIOGRAPHY %%</span>
<span class="c">% Bibliography %</span>
<span class="k">\usepackage</span><span class="na">[backend=biber, style=authoryear-comp, sorting=nyt, maxcitenames=2]</span><span class="p">{</span>biblatex<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="k">\addbibresource</span><span class="p">{</span>ref.bib<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="k">\renewcommand*</span><span class="p">{</span><span class="k">\nameyeardelim</span><span class="p">}{</span><span class="k">\addcomma\space</span><span class="p">}</span> <span class="c">%Add comma between author and year</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">backend=biber</code> specifies that Biber should be used as the backend processor for managing and processing the bibliography.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">style=authoryear-comp</code>: sets the citation and bibliography style to a compact version of the author-year citation style that shows the author’s name and year of publication in citations.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sorting=nyt</code>: defines the order in which the bibliography entries are sorted. The value <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nyt</code> stands for: <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">n</code>: Name of the author</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">y</code>: Year of publication</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">t</code>: Title of the work</li> </ul> </li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">maxcitenames=2</code>: limits the number of author names displayed in a citation to two. If a work has more than two authors, it will show the first author followed by “<em>et al.</em>”</li> </ul> <p>There are several styles you can choose from; you can find a list <a href="https://www.overleaf.com/learn/latex/Biblatex_citation_styles">here</a>. Here, you can also change how entries will be sorted in your bibliography and the maximum number of author names to display.</p> <h2 id="wrapping-up">Wrapping Up</h2> <p>Managing your bibliography effectively is crucial for maintaining the quality and credibility of your thesis. By using Zotero with BibLaTeX, you can streamline the process of collecting, organizing, and citing your sources, ensuring that your references are consistent and accurate. Whether you are working locally or using Overleaf, these tools can significantly simplify your writing workflow.</p> <p>In this post, we covered the basics of setting up Zotero, exporting your references to a BibTeX file, and integrating them into your LaTeX document using BibLaTeX. We’ve also seen how to customize your citation and bibliography styles to fit your needs.</p> <p>Next week, we will talk about customizing the look and feel of your thesis, including fonts, headings, page layout, and margins.</p> <p>Happy writing, and see you next time!</p>]]></content><author><name>Martina Lucà</name></author><category term="LaTeX"/><category term="bibliography"/><category term="thesis"/><category term="latex"/><category term="zotero"/><category term="biblatex"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Simplify your thesis writing process by managing your bibliography with Zotero and BibLaTeX. Learn how to set up, export, and customize your references seamlessly!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Writing a thesis in LaTeX</title><link href="https://martiluca.github.io/blog/2024/writing-a-thesis-with-latex/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Writing a thesis in LaTeX"/><published>2024-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://martiluca.github.io/blog/2024/writing-a-thesis-with-latex</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://martiluca.github.io/blog/2024/writing-a-thesis-with-latex/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="why-latex">Why LaTeX?</h2> <p>What is LaTeX, and why should you use it to write your thesis? LaTeX is a typesetting system widely used in academia, particularly for technical and scientific documents, which offers a series of advantages over traditional word processors:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Superior Typesetting Quality and Consistent Formatting.</strong> One of LaTeX’s best qualities is its consistency, which ensures that your thesis not only reads well but also looks professional.</li> <li><strong>Great Handling of Mathematical Content.</strong> Thesis in STEM fields often involve an extensive use of mathematical formulas and equations. LaTeX provides a powerful equation editor that allows you to write and format complex equations with ease; moreover, referencing them is easy, thanks to the labeling system.</li> <li><strong>Efficient Citation Management.</strong> Thanks to tools like BibTeX and BibLaTeX, managing references and citations is fast and efficient.</li> <li><strong>Flexibility and Customization.</strong> LaTeX offers many customization options. You can tailor the appearance of your thesis to meet specific guidelines or personal preferences. You can change the look of a whole document in a matter of seconds, and it will keep its consistency.</li> <li><strong>Learning and Community Support.</strong> Although LaTeX has a steeper learning curve than traditional word processors, the investment in learning it pays off. Moreover, a vast community of LaTeX users and a wealth of resources are available, including tutorials, templates, and forums where you can seek and share advice.</li> </ol> <h2 id="ok-but-where-do-i-start">Ok, but where do I start?</h2> <p>With that said, where should you start when trying to learn LaTeX? In my opinion, the easiest way is to use an online editor like <a href="https://it.overleaf.com/">Overleaf</a>, which does not require you to install anything and allows for real-time collaboration for free. This has its limitations (it’s slow at compiling, and the free plan also has a compilation time limit), but it’s a great starting point. Pair this with the hundreds of templates already available on this and other websites, and you will be writing documents in no time.</p> <p>In this article, I will explain how to use my particular template, which can be found here, but you can try to follow along with similar templates. One I highly suggest taking a look at once you grasp LaTeX basics is <a href="https://it.overleaf.com/latex/templates/classic-thesis-style-v4-dot-2-by-andre-miede/dwgtvykzvdtk">Classic Thesis</a> by André Miede.</p> <h3 id="the-title-page">The Title Page</h3> <p>Once you downloaded the zip and opened it with your preferred editor (on Overleaf, you can start a new project by simply uploading the zip file), you will see the following file structure:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>.
├── backmatter/
│   └── acknowledgements.tex
├── chapters/
│   └── introduction.tex
├── figures
├── frontmatter/
│   ├── abstract.tex
│   ├── dedication.tex
│   ├── logo.png
│   └── titlepage.tex
├── settings/
│   ├── fonts/
│   ├── commands.tex
│   └── config.tex
├── main.tex
├── ref.bib
└── SciThesis.cls
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Once you understand how this structure works, you can easily add and remove things. First, let’s change the Title Page! To do so, all you have to do is open the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">config.tex</code> file: here, you can insert your university name, department, course, title, supervisors’ name, academic year, and your name and matriculation number.</p> <div class="alert alert-important"> <div class="title"> <span>Important</span> <span><i class="fa-regular fa-message"></i></span> </div> <p> This template uses custom fonts! You will have to change the compiler from pdfLaTeX to either XeLaTeX or LuaLaTeX! </p> <p> To do so in overleaf, click the Menu button in the top left corner. You will find the compiler option in the Settings section. </p> <p> If you are using VSCode with LaTeX Workshop, I have included the appropriate flag at the start of the document (`%!TEX program = lualatex`). All you have to do is enabling magic comments by changing the setting forceRecipeUsage to false. </p> </div> <h3 id="managing-and-adding-chapters">Managing and adding chapters</h3> <p>As you can see, I added a dedication page. You can choose to remove it by removing or commenting the following lines in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main.tex</code> file:</p> <div class="language-latex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c">% Dedication</span>
<span class="k">\include</span><span class="p">{</span>frontmatter/dedication<span class="p">}</span>
    
<span class="c">% insert blank page</span>
<span class="k">\newpage</span>
<span class="k">\thispagestyle</span><span class="p">{</span>empty<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="k">\mbox</span><span class="p">{}</span>
<span class="k">\newpage</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>To modify other sections, like the abstract or the introduction, you can go to their respective files: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">./frontmatter/abstract.tex</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">./chapters/introduction.tex</code>. If you want to add another section, do so by creating the relative tex file in the appropriate folder; then add it to the main document by including it in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main.tex</code> file: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">\include{path/to/document.tex}</code>.</p> <div class="alert alert-tip"> <div class="title"> <span>Tip</span> <span><i class="fa-regular fa-lightbulb"></i></span> </div> <p> If you are having troubles with anything, you can refer to the Overleaf tutorials. Usually, you can find everything you may need there. Moreover, I suggest the <a href="https://www.packtpub.com/product/latex-cookbook-second-edition/9781835080320">LaTeX Cookbook</a> by Stefan Kottwitz, a book that teaches you how to solve common problems when using LaTeX. </p> </div> <h3 id="customization">Customization</h3> <p>You can customize how things look in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SciThesis.cls</code>file. Here, you can manage packages and other layout preferences.</p> <p>You can customize how theorems, code portions, labels, and other things look.</p> <p>The easiest thing you can customize is the main color for the Chapters and links:</p> <div class="language-latex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>40 <span class="k">\definecolor</span><span class="p">{</span>maincolor<span class="p">}{</span>RGB<span class="p">}{</span>51,127,128<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Here, you can change the RGB definition to any color you want. The default one is teal.</p> <h2 id="whats-next">What’s next?</h2> <p>This is just an introductory post to get this template up and running. In the next weeks, I will write more specific tutorials on how to handle common situations you may encounter when writing your thesis, starting with bibliography management.</p> <p>See you next time!</p>]]></content><author><name>Martina Lucà</name></author><category term="LaTeX"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="thesis"/><category term="latex"/><category term="template"/><category term="stem"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Why you should write your thesis in LaTeX? Start here and give it a try!]]></summary></entry></feed>